A Guide to the Allen and Oliver Records, 1849-1955
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Allen and Oliver Records, 1849-1955
Library of Virginia
28049a-b
21 boxes
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of C.H. Oliver, 23 April 1973.
Biographical/Historical Information
Allen and Oliver was a general store that operated in King and Queen County, Virginia. The store also operated under the names W.B. Bird and Son, Allen and Company, Bird and Allen, Taylor and Allen, and finally as Allen and Oliver. Principals involved with the company were Roland D. Allen, Spottswood Bird, William B. Bird, Claibourne H. Oliver (1886-1974), and various other members of their families. The store sold dry goods, groceries, boots and shoes, hardware, china and glassware, and patent medicines. The company was also involved in the purchase and shipment of wood from the docks at Courthouse Landing, King and Queen County, Virginia. Several of the principals, most notably Roland D. Allen, were involved in the operation of the Mantapike Canning Company, producers of "King and Queen Brand" tomatoes. Allen and Claibourne H. Oliver also served as postmaster, the post office being located in the store. The store ceased operation at Oliver’s death in 1974.
Scope and Content Information
The Allen and Oliver Records are housed in 21 boxes and arranged in two series. Series have been designated for Company Records (acc. 28049a) and Postmaster’s Records (28049b).
Series I. The Company Records, 1849-1955, of the Allen and Oliver general store include accounts, correspondence, daybooks, invoices, journals, ledgers, cancelled checks, and receipts. Includes bills of lading for lumber shipped by Allen and Oliver to Ryland and Brooks Lumber Company and American International Lumber; accounts with Ryland and Brooks Lumber Company (Baltimore, Md.) and International Harvester Company of America; certificates of inspection with the Lumber Exchange of Baltimore (Md.), 1916-1926; inspectors reports from Henrico Lumber Company, 1916-1925; and orders from Ryland & Brooks Lumber Company and W.E. Robinson & Company canned goods packers, Henrico Lumber Company, and American Lumber Company. A farm journal, 1872-1888, appears to be for Benvenue Farm and may have been kept by Spottswood Bird. A memorandum book, 1883-1888, notes payments made, mail received and sent, and ship loadings and departures. In some instances copies of letters sent have been transcribed in the memorandum book.
Correspondence includes incoming and outgoing letters with the various firms that the company dealt, 1907-1926. Correspondents include the American Lumber Company; Bird, Ford and Company; Chesapeake Pulp and Paper Company; C.R. Disharoon Company; Henrico Lumber Company, Henry P. Havens, ship broker; and Ryland and Brooks Lumber Company, for which Spottswood Bird is listed as treasurer. Most of the correspondence relates to the purchase and sale of lumber. Also included is correspondence with Mantapike Canning Company. Personal and business correspondence of Spottswood Bird is also included. Among family correspondents are Bird’s sister, Ella Purcell, his sons, Spottswood Jr., Albert, Clifford, and Temple Bird, and his daughter Jean.
Series II. The Postmaster’s Records, 1895-1937, include account and records books, and money order cash books. The account and record books, 1895-1918, include information on daily transactions of stamps, number of stamps on hand, cash amounts of stamps sold, and rent for post office boxes. The money order cashbooks, 1898-1922, include daily listings of the amounts of money orders sold. The register of money orders issued, 1898-1937, includes listings of orders purchased, the name of remitter, name of payee, and amount of order.
Contents List
- Seriers I: Allen and Oliver Company Records, 1849-1955
  - Accounts, 1907-1908 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Accounts, 1914-1916 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Accounts, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Accounts, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Accounts, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Accounts, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Accounts, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Accounts, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Accounts, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Accounts 1924 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Accounts, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Accounts, 1926-1927 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Accounts, nd (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bank statements, 1907-1908 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Bills of lading, 1915-1926 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1907 January-August (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1907 September-December (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1912-1915 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1922-1923 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1924-1925 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, Bird, Spottswood, 1897 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, Bird, Spottswood, 1904 January-June (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, Bird, Spottswood, 1904 July-December (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Bird, Spottswood, 1905 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Bird, Spottswood, 1906 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Bird, Spottswood, 1907 January-June (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Bird, Spottswood, 1907 July-December (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Bird, Spottswood, 1908 January-April (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, Bird, Spottswood, 1908 May-December (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, Bird, Spottswood, 1914 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Bird, Spottswood, nd (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Industrial Commission of Virginia, 1922-1923 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Inspection certificates, 1916-1926 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Inspectors reports, 1916-1925 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous, 1914-1924 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Orders, 1907-1925 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Receipts, 1916-1925 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Cancelled checks, 1903-1954 (Box 5)
  - Volume, Account of shadd sales, 1902-1905 (Box 6)
  - Volume, Account with Spottswood Bird, Jr., 1912-1915 (Box 6)
  - Volume, Daybook, 1892-1894 (Box 7)
  - Volume, Daybook, 1913 April-July (Box 7)
  - Volume, Daybook, 1913 July-November (Box 7)
  - Volume, Daybook, 1914 April-September (Box 8)
  - Volume, Daybook, 1914 September-December (Box 8)
  - Volume, Daybook, 1914 December-1915 April (Box 8)
  - Volume, Daybook, 1915 April-July (Box 8)
  - Volume, Daybook, 1915 July-October (Box 9)
  - Volume, Daybook, 1915 October-1916 February (Box 9)
  - Volume, Daybook, 1916 February-May (Box 9)
  - Volume, Daybook, 1916 May-August (Box 9)
  - Volume, Daybook, 1916 August-November (Box 10)
  - Volume, Daybook, 1916 November-1917 April (Box 10)
  - Volume, Daybook, 1917 July-November (Box 10)
  - Volume, Daybook, 1917 November-1918 April (Box 10)
  - Volume, Daybook, 1918 April-October (Box 11)
  - Volume, Daybook, 1918 October-1919 April (Box 11)
  - Volume, Daybook, 1919 April-December (Box 11)
  - Volume, Daybook, 1920 January-November (Box 11)
  - Volume, Daybook, 1920-1921 (Box 12)
  - Volume, Daybook, 1925 February-1927 July (Box 12)
  - Volume, Daybook, 1927 July-1931 August (Box 13)
  - Volume, Daybook, 1937-1946 (Box 13)
  - Volume, Daybook, 1946-1955 (Box 14)
  - Volume, Farm account book, 1872-1882 (Box 14)
  - Volume, Index to William B. Bird Ledger "E", 1873 (Box 14)
  - Volume, Index, unidentified, nd (Box 14)
  - Volume, Journal, 1908-1917 (Box 15)
  - Volume, Journal, 1921-1926 (Box 15)
  - Volume, Journal, 1934-1941 (Box 15)
  - Volume, Journal, 1942-1952 (Box 15)
  - Volume, Purchase journal, 1889-1895 (Box 16)
  - Volume, Purchase journal, 1916-1931 (Box 16)
  - Volume, Ledger, 1849-1852 (Box 16)
  - Volume, Ledger, 1905-1906 (Box 16)
  - Volume, Ledger, 1907-1939 (Box 17)
  - Volume, Ledger, 1912-1913 (Box 17)
  - Volume, Ledger, 1917-1919 (Box 17)
  - Volume, Memorandum book, 1883-1888 (Box 18)
- Seriers II: Postmasters Records, 1895-1937
  - Account and record book, 1895-1899 (Box 19)
  - Account and record book, 1905-1908 (Box 19)
  - Account and record book, 1908-1911 (Box 19)
  - Account and record book, 1917-1918 (Box 19)
  - Money order cash books, 1898-1907 (Box 20)
  - Money order cash books, 1914-1918 (Box 20)
  - Money order cash books, 1918-1922 (Box 20)
  - Rent book for Post Office boxes, 1914-1916 (Box 20)
  - Registers of Money Order Issued, 1898-1921 (Box 21)
  - Registers of Money Order Issued, 1925-1929 (Box 21)
  - Registers of Money Order Issued, 1929-1933 (Box 21)
  - Register of Money Order Advices received, 1898-1937 (Box 21)